<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Four Short Stories: A Digital Edition</title>
            <author>
               <persName>Fanny Van de Grift Stevenson</persName>
            </author>
            <editor> Dr Robyn Pritzker </editor>
            <funder> Centre for Data, Culture, and Society: University of Edinburgh </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <ab><!-- unpublished manuscripts with permission of the Robert Louis Stevenson Museum in St. Helena, California--></ab>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>St. Helena, California</settlement>
                  <repository>Robert Louis Stevenson Museum</repository>
                  <idno>Scrapbook 1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="ScribeA" scribeRef="FVS">Clear, cursive script</handNote>
         </handNotes>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>



   <text>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <div hand="#ScribeA">
            <head type="title">Ah Choon and the Sorcerer</head>
            <p> A Chinese fisherman of <placeName corresp="stevensonography.xml#amoy"
                  >Amoy</placeName> for many days had cast his nets only to draw them to land empty.
               Walking the streets that he might there-by forget in some degree the hunger that
               assailed him, he encountered a figure that arrested his attention. It was that of a
               beggar apparently in the most abject destitution. His skin was filthy, and he was
               clothed in rags; <span ana="stevensonography.xml#wonder">There was a weird strange
                  look in his eyes, and a gleam of intelligence at variance with his condition shone
                  through the dirt that encrusted his face.</span>
               <persName corresp="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon">Ah Choon</persName>, the fisherman,
               felt that somewhere before he had met <seg corresp="stevensonography.xml#sorcerer"
                  >the beggar</seg> when he presented a very different aspect. At last it <said
                  who="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon" toWhom="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon"
                  aloud="false" direct="false">occurred to him that it must be an emperor’s
                  sorcerer,</said> who had probably chosen this disguise that he might walk the
               streets undisturbed by the prayers and solicitations of those who believed in his
               powers.</p>
            <p><seg corresp="stevensonography.xml#sorcerer">This great magician</seg>
               <said who="stevensonography.xml#narratorD" direct="false">was said to know</said> all
               things known to man or devils. <span ana="stevensonography.xml#wonder">He could
                  foretell deaths, and the rise and fall of empires, so great was his knowledge that
                  the spirits of the air had limited him in his prophecies.</span>
               <span ana="stevensonography.xml#gothic">If he told all he knew fierce lightning would
                  burst from the sky and devour him in its fire.</span></p>
            <p><persName corresp="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon">Ah Choon </persName>bowed his head
               to the ground before <seg corresp="stevensonography.xml#sorcerer">the sorcerer</seg>
               and cried <said who="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon"
                  toWhom="stevensonography.xml#sorcerer" aloud="true">“give me something I beseech
                  you” <!-- problem here? Check source --> Give me something, I beseech you or I
                  will implore you forever!”</said></p>
            <p><said who="stevensonography.xml#sorcerer" toWhom="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon"
                  aloud="true" direct="true">“Rise my son,” said <seg
                     corresp="stevensonography.xml#sorcerer">the sorcerer</seg>, “How can I give you
                  what I have not myself? You see I am but a wretched beggar; it is you who must
                  give to me.”</said></p>
            <p><persName corresp="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon">Ah Choon</persName> still besought
               him until the old man losing patience thrust him on one side. As he did so, <persName
                  corresp="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon">Ah Choon</persName> snatched from his
               breast a handful of the beggar’s rags and ran to cast his nets, throwing into them as
               he did a scrap of the rags. <pb/> The nets came up bursting with fine large fish.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon">Ah Choon</persName> hied him to the
               market where he soon disposed of his fish for a good sum and went home his pockets
               heavy with cash.</p>
            <p>The next day <seg corresp="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon">he</seg> cast his nets again
               with the same good luck. But when he went to the market to sell his fish <seg
                  corresp="stevensonography.xml#mob">a jabbering crowd</seg> surrounded him. <said
                  who="stevensonography.xml#mob" toWhom="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon">“Cheat!
                  Swindler” They cried “Who sold us <seg ana="stevensonography.xml#wonder">enchanted
                     fish</seg> that were fat and large when we bought them, and but empty air when
                  we opened our baskets!”</said></p>
            <p><seg corresp="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon">The Fisherman</seg>
               <kinesic/>turned pale. <!-- missing inv comma(s)? -->
               <said who="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon" toWhom="stevensonography.xml#mob"
                  aloud="true">Here, my friends, he cried. choose from those I have caught today,
                  and if the same thing happens again you will help me to find and punish <seg
                     corresp="stevensonography.xml#sorcerer">the wicked sorcerer</seg> who has put a
                  cheat both upon you and me!” And he told his story to <seg
                     corresp="stevensonography.xml#mob">the gaping crowd.</seg></said></p>
            <p>When they turned to fill their baskets, no fish were there; only a few fresh leaves.
                  <persName corresp="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon">Ah Choon</persName> felt a chill
               at his back. Turning he beheld <seg corresp="stevensonography.xml#sorcerer">the
                  sorcerer</seg> in his beggar’s garb. All perceived him at the same moment.</p>
            <p><said who="stevensonography.xml#mob" aloud="true">“Tis he!” They cried, “Tear him to
                  pieces!”</said> And rushed forward to attack him. He smiled. <said
                  who="stevensonography.xml#sorcerer" toWhom="stevensonography.xml#mob" aloud="true"
                  >“One moment my children.” he said, “and you may do with me as you will. Let me
                  amuse you first.”</said> As he said this he spat on the ground a black spittle
               into which he dipped the end of his long finger and drew figures upon a white wall.
                  <span ana="stevensonography.xml#gothic">As he drew the figures sprang from under
                  his fingers, writhing over the wall in a hideous manner. The gaze of all who
                  waited upon the little friends who leered at the spectators changed heads with
                  each other, spread their mouths from ear to ear in demonish glee, struck at each
                  other, and contorted their limbs.</span> So <seg ana="stevensonography.xml#gothic"
                  >frightful an exhibition</seg> did it finally become that <seg
                  corresp="stevensonography.xml#mob">the mob with one accord turned and fled.</seg>
               Some of the boldest looking back saw <seg corresp="stevensonography.xml#sorcerer">the
                  sorcerer</seg>, still serenely smiling, strike the figures dead with his staff,
               wrap with rags about him and melt into a light gray cloud, which gradually dissolved
               into the air. After that time <seg corresp="stevensonography.xml#ahchoon">the
                  fisherman’s</seg> luck was variable, but he tried no more <seg
                  corresp="stevensonography.xml#wonder">magic arts</seg> to increase his gains.</p>
         </div>

      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="editorial">
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="narratorD"> </person>
               <person xml:id="ahchoon">
                  <persName>Ah Choon</persName>
                  <sex value="M"/>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>humanoid</label>
                  </trait>
                  <trait type="profession">
                     <label>Fisherman</label>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>Mermaiden</persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="sorcerer">
                  <persName>Sorcerer of the Sea</persName>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label> Humanoid Wizard </label>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <personGrp xml:id="mob">
                  <persName> the crowd </persName>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label> human </label>
                  </trait>
               </personGrp>
            </listPerson>
            <interpGrp type="charActs">
               <interp xml:id="grief">indicating a character's display of grief, sadness,
                  loss.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="fear">indicating a character's display of fear, anger, terror,
                  distress.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="joy">indicating a character's display of joy, happiness.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="unsure">indicating a character's display of uncertainty, mistrust, or
                  confusion.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
            <interpGrp type="genre">
               <interp xml:id="gothic">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the Gothic
                  genre.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="wonder">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the wonder tale
                  genre.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
