<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Four Short Stories: A Digital Edition</title>
            <author>
               <persName>Fanny Van de Grift Stevenson</persName>
            </author>
            <editor> R Pritzker </editor>
            <funder> Centre for Data, Culture, and Society: University of Edinburgh </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <ab><!-- unpublished manuscripts with permission of the Robert Louis Stevenson Museum in St. Helena, California--></ab>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>St. Helena, California</settlement>
                  <repository>Robert Louis Stevenson Museum</repository>
                  <idno>Scrapbook 1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="ScribeA" scribeRef="FVS">Clear, cursive script</handNote>
         </handNotes>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div hand="#ScribeA">
            <head type="title">Borriballoo</head>
            <p>
               <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda Smith found herself in a
               very unpleasant position. How it happened is not part of this story, which opens with
                  <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda hanging by the belt on a
               hook <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#wonder">in a giant’s kitchen. </span></p>
            <p>The cook was heating water, and sharpening knives for the evident purpose of
               preparing <ref corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>the unhappy girl for the
               giant’s table, she was just in the act of studying <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda’s length and breadth with an eye
               to a dripping pan of the right proportions when the giant entered. </p>
            <p><persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda could see nothing in her
                  <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#fear"> terror but a huge unshapely bulk of
                  frightful aspect. </span> Really, however, <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant"/>the giant possessed a jolly, big
               good-humoured stupid face. Jolly people are apt to be a little stupid.</p>
            <p><said aloud="true">“No luck again, today.”</said> He said, as he came thumping in.
                  <said aloud="true">“A pretty dish to sit before the grand Borriballoo, one pitiful
                  child with a spoonful of gravy; and too late today for any more hunting. Is she
                  nice and plump?”</said> as he advanced toward the <span
                  ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#fear">terrified Belinda</span>.</p>
            <p><said aloud="true">“Halloo! What’s this?!</said>
               <!-- Insert closing quote? --> Stooping to pick up a bit of paper that had dropped
               from <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda’s pocket. As he
               glanced over the note, which was only a wash bill from Belinda’s mother, who did
               clearstacking, his countenance changed; he sighed heavily, and <said
                  who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant" direct="true"/> repeated the name signed to the
               note several times in a <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#grief">sad and touching
                  voice</span>; then reached up and unhooked <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda whom he placed upon a table by his
               side.</p>
            <p><said who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant" aloud="true">“What is your name,
                  child?”</said> he asked, in a very different voice from that he had used when he
               entered. <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>
               <said who="giant" aloud="true"> “Belinda Smith, you say? Ah yes, that name I have
                  heard before. It is truly a sweet name. You would hardly believe now, that a
                  <!-- unclear word -->bluff old fellow like myself had ever been in love? I have.
                  It was your mother child. Many years ago she fell into my hands much as you have
                  done; I had intended her for company, but before long she had <pb/>somehow wound
                  herself into my affections, she implored me to carry her to her father. I did so.
                  From that day to this I have never beheld her. I know now that it would have been
                  better to have eaten her as I intended to do, for then she would have been part of
                  my own being forever. Now it is too late. Like you, she was very plump,”</said>
               looking dreamily at <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda.</p>
            <p><said aloud="true">“I think, my dear, for the sake of old times, and the memories of
                  my youth, I will have you served with my guests instead of to them. Come, I will
                  call <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog, my son to
                  show you to the guest chamber. Try to rest and sleep well that your eyes may be as
                  bright, and your cheeks as rosy as your mothers were when I first saw
               her.”</said></p>
            <p><persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog came at <said
                  direct="true">his father’s call </said> and escorted <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda to her room. He was a saucy
               awkward lout of a giant boy and disposed to be sulky at the change in the morrow’s
               bill of fare.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda was too tired to think of
               the strange things that had occurred, and <said direct="true"
                  who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"> begging <persName
                     corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog to reach a pillow for her
                  from the immense bed, </said> she lay down upon it and slept until daybreak. In
               the morning it was some time before she could recall her scattered senses enough to
               recollect her whereabouts; but <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#lallagagog"
               />Lallagagog’s hoarse voice <said direct="true"> calling her to breakfast,</said>
               warned her to be in haste. She dressed rapidly and stepped into the hall where
                  <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant"/>the giant was waiting for her. He
               led her into the breakfast room. A box had been placed upon a chair for her and the
               giant lifted her to her place. Her <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#fear">acutest
                  fears</span> now began to dissipate, and she ate her breakfast with a good
               appetite, and even <said who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda" direct="true">carried on
                  a conversation with the giant with some diplomacy, giving full accounts of all the
                  members of the Smith family</said> that she knew anything about, especially of
               those who had become famous or possessed much political influence, hoping that the <pb/>
               <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant"/>giant might <span
                  ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#fear">have some fear of incurring the enmity of so great
                  and influential a race.</span></p>
            <p>The giant listened politely, and looked impressed by what she had said. Suddenly a
               bright idea seemed to strike him.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/><said aloud="true"
                  who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant">“Belinda,” said he kindly, “How old are
                  you?</said></p>
            <p><said aloud="true" who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda">“Fifteen.”</said></p>
            <p><said aloud="true" who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant">“My grandmother was married at
                  fifteen,” </said> remarked <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant"/>the
               giant.</p>
            <p><said aloud="true" who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda">“Was she indeed?”</said> said
                  <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/> Belinda, not knowing what else
               to say.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>
               <said who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant" aloud="true">“Belinda,” more kindly still,
                  “How would you like to be married?”</said></p>
            <p><span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#fear">A horrible fear took possession of <persName
                     corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda. </span> Perhaps he wished to
               marry her himself. He must be a widower, she had seen no woman, yet, about the house
               but the cook, and for all she knew, giants might, anyhow, have as many wives as old
                  <ref target="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Brigham-Young"
               >Brigham.</ref></p>
            <p><said who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda" aloud="true">“I—I don’t—know” </said>
               faltered poor <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda, <span
                  ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#grief">bursting into tears.</span></p>
            <p><said who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant" aloud="true">“Tut, tut, Pshaw!” said <persName
                     corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant"/>the giant in not so kind a voice as
                  before. “I’m not going to eat you, what are you crying for?”</said></p>
            <p>The cry was swallowed instantly, as <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"
               />Belinda made haste to answer <said who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda" aloud="true"
                  >“I never thought of such a thing, I assure you! What were you about to say,
                  please?” </said>with a sickly attempt to smile.</p>
            <p><said aloud="true" who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant">“Only this,” said <persName
                     corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant"/>the giant, “that I am going to have
                  company today to dinner; a personnage of great importance;” his voice took a
                  deeper tone. “His Highness the <persName
                     corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>Grand Borriballoo! It is to be
                  quite an affair as it is only a business interview he seeks. “I,” and he <kinesic
                     who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant"/>swelled with conscious pride, “am
                  Confidential Matrimonial Adviser to his highness! Of course a personage of his
                  rank could not take the trouble to choose a wife for himself. That is my
                  affair.<pb/> I have been in <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#unsure"> much
                     perplexity </span> because I could not fix upon an eligible party, when it
                  suddenly occurred to me, why not <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"
                  />Belinda? You are certainly of a good family, belonging to a long line of Smiths.
                  And being a protegee of mine gives you standing. Indeed, I consider it a very
                  suitable match on both sides. Now, my dear, just think this matter over. At four
                  precisely I will come for your decision.” </said>Bowing politely he left the
               room.</p>
            <p><span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#joy">Belinda was in a whirl of agitation. What a
                  brilliant future was before her!</span> The <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>Borriballoo, might, to be sure, be as
               old and ugly as the giant himself: but the bliss of being “My Lady Borriballoo”
               covered any unpleasant suggestions that arose in her mind. An occasional thought of
               the red headed boy, who sat next to her at school, and to whom she had been engaged
               for the past three weeks came to her remembrance once or twice, but was soon
               forgotten. What chance had a red headed boy beside the grand <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>Borriballoo.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda had one ugly habit of which
               I am loth to speak. She was very apt to put her thumb in her mouth when thinking. She
               did so upon this occasion, as she sat wrapped in her reflections, <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog, who had been drowning flies
               in the cream, and amusing himself in other kindred ways, now turned his attention to
                  <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda, stepping up softly
               behind her, he placed one great hand upon her head, the other under her chin, and
               suddenly snapped her teeth together with a loud laugh.</p>
            <p><persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#lallagagog"/><span
                  ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#gothic"> Lallagagog did a worse mischief than he had
                  intended. His hands were so strong, and the little white teeth so sharp, that
                     <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda was placed in the
                  awkward predicament of having bitten off her own thumb.</span></p>
            <p><persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog ran off and hid
               himself, and poor <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda retired,
                  <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#grief">weeping</span>, to her chamber to bind up
               her mutilated hand <pb/>and invent an excuse for not appearing at dinner; for she
               hardly liked to make her first appearance before the <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>Borriballoo with a red nose and
               swollen eyes, and a bandaged hand.</p>
            <p>She finally <said who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda" aloud="true" direct="true">
                  pleaded a headache</said>, <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#unsure">a feeling of
                  uncertainty and insecurity</span> prompting her not to complain of <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog.</p>
            <p>When <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant"/>the giant saw her <span
                  ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#grief">woebegone face</span>, he very readily excused
               her, <said who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant" aloud="true">saying that if such was her
                  pleasure, he would make all necessary arrangements himself</said>.</p>
            <p><span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#joy"> Ambition and pride</span> rose in <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda’s heart, she gave her full consent
               to the proposed marriage.</p>
            <p>In the evening, <said who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant" aloud="true">the giant said
                  that the grand <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>Borriballoo
                  was perfectly satisfied with the description and account given of the bride elect,
                  and only desired that she should be allowed to remain in strict seclusion until
                  the day of the ceremony, in accordance with the customs of his
               ancestors.</said></p>
            <p>Preparations for the wedding went on apace, and at length the day arrived. The great
               hall of <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant"/>the giant’s mansion was
               decorated with the most elegant taste, and hundreds of brilliant lights flashed upon
               the jewels and rich dresses of the guests.</p>
            <p>At opposite ends of the hall were great doors. These were thrown open simultaneously.
               Through one entered the <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>Grand
               Borriballoo leaning upon the arm of the priest, at the same moment that <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda supported by <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant"/>the giant appeared at the other. <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog followed bearing her
               train.</p>
            <p>All eyes were turned towards <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>the
               bride; but she saw nothing but the <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>Grand Borriballoo, whom she now met
               for the first time. <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#wonder"> His carriage was
                  majestic, and at the same time of a very peculiar grace, caused doubtless by his
                  having three legs, instead of the usual number. His glittering tail was so
                  <pb/>long that as he stood in the centre of the room its extremity reached to the
                  entrance where it was borne by five and twenty pages in gold and white. His heavy
                  locks of ferns and field flowers fell to his waist. His eye, placed in the centre
                  of his forehead, was large and lustrous and full. In short, the most fastidious
                  person could have taken no exception to his personal appearance.</span></p>
            <p>A <kinesic ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#joy"/>sudden hush and expectant thrill fell upon
               the vast assembly as the <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>grand
               Borriballoo advanced towards <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"
               />Belinda, <kinesic who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>tenderly took her hand,
               gazed long and earnestly into her face, and signed the priest to continue Why will
               not the fates allow me to stop here, nor further follow <span
                  ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#gothic">this tale which so suddenly changes to a scene
                  of gloom and horror.</span></p>
            <p>As <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda, blushing, raised her
               hand to receive the ring from the <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>Royal Borriballoo, the priest gently
               said <said who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#priest" aloud="true">“Your right thumb, if you
                  please; it is the law that only thus a grand <persName
                     corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>Borriballoo may marry."</said>
               <!-- editorial: inserted closing quotation mark above [marry."] --></p>
            <p>Unconsciously <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda raised her
               maimed right hand.</p>
            <p><span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#fear">The priest <kinesic
                     who="FSTEI_Ography_120719#priest"/>shrank back with a cry of horror, and the
                     <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>Grand Borriballoo fell to
                  the floor in a deathlike swoon.</span></p>
            <p>“Ah I shall burst with mortification!” Groaned <persName
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#giant"/>the giant, which he immediately did with a
               loud report.</p>
            <p><span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#fear">The guests fled in terror, some of them
                  mortally wounded.</span></p>
            <p>The ring, which had dropped from the hand of the bridegroom rolled along the floor to
               the feet of <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#lallagagog"/>Lallagagog, who
               shyly hid it in his mouth. It stuck in his windpipe. <span
                  ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#gothic">In the confusion caused by his father’s
                  explosion he was unnoticed, and soon choked to death.</span></p>
            <p>The whole proceedings were so frightfully indecorous that <pb/><span
                  ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#fear">the priest fell into a rage, which was so deep
                  that no ropes would reach him, where he remains to this day.</span></p>
            <p>The end of the <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo"/>grand
               Borriballoo was <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#grief">sad beyond belief. Knowing his
                  union with <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda was now
                  impossible, he fell into a low state, weeping incessantly, neglecting the affairs
                  connected with his rank and office, which consequently fell into other hands about
                  whom his old friends rallied.</span></p>
            <p>His society had become so wearisome to those about him that he was left alone more
               and more, so that when he had <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#gothic">wept his eye
                  out</span> so one was aware of the piteous fact, and he wandered for days in <span
                  ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#wonder">a thick wood adjacent to the castle</span>
               vainly seeking his way out. At last, <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#grief">glum and
                  weary, suffering intolerably from thirst and hunger, he sunk upon the
                  ground.</span></p>
            <p>“Ah <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda” moaned he, as he wiped
               the growing cavern where his eye had been, with his tail, “would I had never beheld
               thee!” In his <span ana="FSTEI_Ography_120719#grief"
                  corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#borriballoo">anguish he accidentally placed the end
                  of his tail into his mouth; unconsciously, in his delirium, assailed by the pangs
                  of hunger, he began devouring it, and absently ate himself up. No remains were
                  ever found except a few tail scales that his stomach was unable to
               digest.</span></p>
            <p>As to <persName corresp="FSTEI_Ography_120719#belinda"/>Belinda, no one knows what
               became of her.</p>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="editorial">
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="narratorA"> </person>
               <person xml:id="belinda">
                  <persName>Belinda Smith</persName>
                  <sex value="F"/>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>human</label>
                  </trait>

               </person>
               <person xml:id="lallagagog">
                  <persName>Lallagagog</persName>
                  <sex value="M"/>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>giant</label>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="giant">
                  <persName>the Giant</persName>
                  <sex value="M"/>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>giant</label>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="borriballoo">
                  <persName>Grand Borriballoo</persName>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>humanoid creature</label>
                     <desc>flowers for hair, long glittering tail, three legs</desc>
                  </trait>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="priest">
                  <persName>the priest</persName>
                  <sex value="M"/>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>unknown</label>
                  </trait>
               </person>

               <person>
                  <persName>Sheep</persName>
                  <sex value="F"/>
                  <trait type="species">
                     <label>Sheep</label>
                  </trait>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>Lamb</persName>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName>she-wolf</persName>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <interpGrp type="charActs">
               <interp xml:id="grief">indicating a character's display of grief, sadness,
                  loss.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="fear">indicating a character's display of fear, anger, terror,
                  distress.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="joy">indicating a character's display of joy, happiness.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="unsure">indicating a character's display of uncertainty, mistrust, or
                  confusion.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
            <interpGrp type="genre">
               <interp xml:id="gothic">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the Gothic
                  genre.</interp>
               <interp xml:id="wonder">Relating to themes, trends, conventions of the wonder tale
                  genre.</interp>
            </interpGrp>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
